this is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in the public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
The Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter nine The Queen of the
field-mice We cannot be far from the road of yellow brick, now,” remarked the
Scarecrow, as he stood beside the girl where we have come nearly as far as the
river carried us away.” The Tin Woodman was about to reply when he heard a low
growl, and turning his head (which worked beautifully on hinges) he saw a strange
beast bounding over the grass towards them. It was, indeed, a great yellow
Wildcat, and the Woodman thought it must be chasing something, for its ears were
lying close to its head and its mouth was wide open, showing two rows of ugly
teeth, while it's red eyes glowed like balls of fire. As it came near the Tin
Woodman saw that running before the beast was a little gray field mouse, and
although he had no heart he knew that it was wrong for the wild cat to try to
kill such a pretty, harmless creature. So the Woodman raised his axe, and as the
wild cat ran by he gave it a quick blow that cut the beasts head clean off from
its body, and it rolled over at his feet in two pieces. The field mouse, now that
it was freed from its enemy, stopped short; and coming slowly up to the
Woodman it said, in a squeaky little voice: “Oh, thank you! Thank you ever so
much for saving my life.” “Don’t speak of it, I beg you,” replied the Woodman. “I have
no heart, you know, so I am careful to help all those who may need a friend,
even if it happens to be only a mouse.” “Only a mouse!” cried the little animal,
indignantly. “Why, I am a Queen— —the Queen of all Field Mice!” “Oh, indeed,” said the
Woodman, making a bow. “Therefore you have done a great deed, as well as a brave one,
in saving my life,” added the Queen. At that moment several mice were seen
running up as fast that their little legs could carry them, and when they saw
their Queen they exclaimed: “Oh, your Majesty, we thought you would be killed!
How did you manage to escape the grey Wildcat?” They all bowed so low to the
little Queen that they almost stood upon their heads. “This funny tin man,”
she answered, “killed the Wildcat and saved my life. So hereafter you must all
serve him, and obey his slightest wish.” “We will!” cried all the mice, in a shrill
chorus. And then they scampered in all directions, for Toto had awakened from
his sleep, and seeing all these mice around him gave him one bark of delight
and jumped right into the middle of the group. Toto had always loved to chase
mice when he lived in Kansas, and he saw no harm in it. But the Tin Woodman caught
the dog in his arms and held him tight, while he called to the mice, “Come back!
Come back!
Toto shall not hurt you.” At this the Queen of the Mice stuck her head out
from underneath a clump of grass and asked, in a timid voice, “Are you sure he
will not bite us?” “I will not let him,” said
the Woodman; “so do not be afraid.” One by one the mice came creeping back, and Toto
did not bark again, although he tried to get out of the Woodman’s arms, and would
have bitten him had he not known very well he was made of ten Finally one of
the biggest mice spoke. “Is there anything we can do,” it asked, “to repay you for
saving the life of our Queen?” “Nothing that I know of,” answered the Woodman; but
the Scarecrow, who had been trying to think, but could not because his head was
stuffed with straw, said, quickly, “Oh, yes; you can save our friend, the Cowardly
Lion, who is asleep in the poppy bed.” “A Lion!” cried the little Queen while he
would eat us all up.” “Oh, no,” declared the Scarecrow; “this Lion is a coward.” “Really?”
asked the Mouse. “He says so himself,” answered the Scarecrow, “and he would
never hurt anyone who is our friend. If you will help us to save him I promise
he shall treat you with all kindness.” “Very well,” said the Queen, “we trust you.
But what shall we do?” “Are there many of these mice which call you Queen and are
willing to obey you?” “Oh, yes; there are thousands,” she replied. “Then send for them
all to come here as soon as possible, and let each one bring a long piece of string.”
The Queen turned to the mice that attended her and told them to go at once
and get all her people. As soon as they heard her orders they ran away in every
direction as fast as possible. “Now,” said the Scarecrow to the Tin Woodman, “you
must go to those trees by the riverside and make a truck that will carry the
Lion.” So the Woodman went at once to the trees and began to work; and he soon made
a truck out of the limbs of trees, from which he chopped the way all the leaves
and branches. He fastened it together with wooden pegs and made the four
wheels out of short pieces of a big tree trunk. So fast and so well did he work
that by the time the mice began to arrive the truck was all ready for them.
They came from all directions, and there were thousands of them: big mice and
little mice and middle sized mice; and each one brought a piece of string in
his mouth. It was about this time that Dorothy woke from her long sleep and
opened her eyes. She was greatly astonished to find herself lying upon
the grass, with thousands of mice standing around and looking at her
timidly. But the Scarecrow told her about everything, and turning to the dignified
little Mouse, he said: “Permit me to introduce you to her Majesty, the Queen.”
Dorothy nodded gravely in the Queen made a curtsy, after which she became quite
friendly with the little girl.
The Scarecrow in the Woodman now began to fasten the mice to the truck, using
the strings they had brought. One end of a string was tied around the neck of
each mouse and the other end to the truck. Of course the truck was a thousand
times bigger than any of the mice who were to draw it; but when all the mice
had been harnessed, they were able to pull it quite easily. Even the Scarecrow
and the Tin Woodman could sit on it, and were drawn swiftly by their queer little
horses to the place where the Lion lay asleep. After a great deal of hard work,
for the Lion was heavy, they managed to get him up on the truck. Then the Queen
hurriedly gave her people the order to start where she feared if the mice
stayed among the poppies too long they also would fall asleep. At first the
little creatures Minnie though they were, could hardly stir the heavily loaded
truck; but the Woodman and the Scarecrow both pushed from behind, and they got along better.
Soon they rolled the Lion out of the poppy bed to the green fields, where they
could breathe the sweet, fresh air again, instead of the poisonous scent of the
flowers. Dorothy came to meet them and thank the little mice warmly for saving
her companion from death. She had grown so fond of the big Lion she was glad he
had been rescued. Then the mice were unharmed from the truck and scampered
away through the grass to their homes.
The Queen of the Mice was the last to leave. “If you ever need us again,” she said,
“come out into the field and call, and we shall hear you and come to your
assistance goodbye goodbye they all answered, and away the Queen ran, while
Dorothy held Toto tightly lest he should run after her and frightened her. After
this they sat down beside the Lion until he should awaken; and the Scarecrow
brought Dorothy some fruit from a tree nearby which she ate for her dinner The
end of Chapter nine